<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>untagged on Diane M's blog</title><link>https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/tags/untagged/</link><description>Recent content in untagged on Diane M's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 19:31:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/tags/untagged/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Developers Work From Home</title><link>https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/posts/work-from-home/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 19:31:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/posts/work-from-home/</guid><description>This blog post propose you a short tour on developers work from home data and a guide towards optimizing remote and in person workplaces. After a short dive in data, I will present strength and challenges of every organization and conclude with recommendations.
Key data Stack overflow study states in 2023 about 42% surveyed developers work in totally remote environment, 42% in hybrid, and 16% in fully in-office.
Self-employed developers work remotely for 70% of them.</description></item><item><title>Green It</title><link>https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/posts/green-it/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 18:53:49 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://princess-entrapta.github.io/blog/posts/green-it/</guid><description>Some figures about IT and the environment Electronic devices and other IT related activity represent 4% of the total global carbon footprint, a figure that is growing every year due to sector growth. If the proportion may look small, it actually is important regarding other industry sectors; automobile sector, known for its pollution side effects, in its whole is for example estimated weighting roughly 6 to 9% of global carbon emissions.</description></item></channel></rss>